<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon on the parable of the sower, taken out of the 13. of Mathew. Preached at London by M. G. Gifford, &amp; published at the request of sundrie godly and well disposed persons</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118278</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01731)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon on the parable of the sower, taken out of the 13. of Mathew. Preached at London by M. G. Gifford, &amp; published at the request of sundrie godly and well disposed persons</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. East] for Tobie Cooke, dwelling at the Tigres head in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sower (Parable) --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18869:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon on the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable of the Sower, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the 13. of Mathew. Preached at London by M. G. Gifford, &amp; publiſhed at the requeſt of ſundrie godly and well diſpoſed perſons.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London for Tobie Cooke, dwelling at the Tigres head in Paules Churchyard. 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18869:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18869:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL M. Iohn Hutton Eſquier, George Gifford <hi>wiſheth health and increaſe of worſhip.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is more then halfe a yere (right worſhipfull) ſince I handled this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Sower, in a Sermon at London, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtantly vrged by a friend which heard mee, to put it in writing, althogh I was very vnw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ng, for ſundrie conſiderations, yet I made ſome promiſe if leſure ſhuld ſerue. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward when I wold very gladly haue ben releaſed at her hands whom I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, I could by no meanes obteine it. I haue therfore at the laſt ſo nigh as I could, ſet down in writing, that which I then vttered in ſpeking, I know that I haue omitted ſome things in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular applications, and exhortations which I made: &amp; alſo I haue added ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which either then came not to mind, or els time did not ſerue to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. I am bolde to preſent &amp; dedicate this my poore trauell vnto your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, moued therto with diuers reſpects as thinking my ſelfe in duetie bound,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:3"/>
not onely with this common &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bond that ye are one which long time haue profeſſed the glorious goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt: but with diuers more ſpeciall, which are ſo wel knowne vnto you, that it wer needleſſe for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them: only thus much, ſeeing I was born &amp; brought vp vnder you, my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents receiuing benefits daily fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, I think I ought, when as I am not able to make any recompence, at leaſt to ſhew ſome token of a grateful mind. But eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially I am moued heerevnto, with conſideration of the greateſt bleſsing which all my kindred haue enioyed by you now ſo long, in prouiding &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing their ſpiritual inſtruction. I pray you accept of my good will, &amp; account of mee as one which praieth to the Lord for you, that he will multiplie &amp; increaſe his good giftes ſtill in you, to the glorie of his holy name, the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Church, &amp; your endleſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours for euer to commaund in the Lord, George Gifford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18869:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon vpon the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Sower.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Math. 13.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>1 IN that day Ieſus went out of the houſe and ſate by the Sea ſide.</p>
                  <p>2 And there was gathered vnto him a multitude, ſo that hee entered into a ſhip, and ſate downe, and the whole multitude ſtood on the ſhoare.</p>
                  <p>3 And he ſpake many things vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Parables, faieng: Behold a Sower went forth to fowe.</p>
                  <p>4 And as he ſowed, ſome ſeeds fell by the way ſide: and the fowles came &amp; eate them vp.</p>
                  <p>5 Other fel vpon ſtonie ground, where they had not much earth, and by &amp; by they ſprang vp, becauſe they had not depth of earth.</p>
                  <p>6 And when the Sun roſe they were parched, and becauſe they had no root they withered.</p>
                  <p>7 Other fell among thornes, and the thornes grew vp and choked it.</p>
                  <p>8 Other fell into good grounde, and brought forth fruit, one ſeed an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth fold, another ſixty, another thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18869:4"/>9 He that hath eares to heare, let him heare.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Iewes, at ſuch time as our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt came into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, had the word of God among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; had alſo the temple &amp; Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues where they heard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame read &amp; expounded: yet their ſtate was very mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, for Chriſt ſaith, they wer as ſhéep without a ſhepheard: becauſe their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scribes &amp; Phareſies, being choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with couetouſnes, &amp; puffed vp with vaine glory, were become ſtark naught, corrupt in manners, and corrupting the word with their fond gloſes: their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo was ſo cold, &amp; with ſo litle pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er euen in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they taught truly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people had no great liſt to heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But when <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> the forerunner of Chriſt, was raiſed vp to publiſh the beginning of the Goſpell, &amp; to prepare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way for the Lord: he like a ſounding &amp; ſhrill Trumpet, with the power of his word ſhooke their hearts, &amp; rowſed their drowſines, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:18869:4"/>
of heuen ſuffered violence. When Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe vttered his voice in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and his diuine power in working wonders, ther appered ſuch a wonderful maieſty in his perſon, as did amaze the hearers: whervpon his fame was noiſed far &amp; néere, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they came running out of all quarters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land by heaps, for to ſée &amp; heare him, they ſéemed to forget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues &amp; their ſtate, in leauing al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaires, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſbandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their plough, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Artificers their craftes &amp; ſciences, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wildernes with their wiues &amp; their children laggering at their héeles, ſo great was their zeale. So that, as before almoſt all did periſh in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate they were in: now it ſéemed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the greateſt part, or at leſt an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable multitude did with ſuch care im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld be moſt happy, &amp; come to eternal life: but this was otherwiſe, for our ſauior Chriſt ſheweth héere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of this gret heap &amp; rable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of people, which wer ſo zealous &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelled ſo far to heare him, ther wer thrée parts which did not profit by his doctrine but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued ſtil damned &amp; forlorne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:5"/>
onely one parte of foure, are true ſchollers. And becauſe we be ranke hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits, prone &amp; redie to deceiue our ſelues, Chriſt Ieſus laieth open the matter ſo plainly, &amp; in ſo familiar a kinde of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnles we wilfully blind our ſelues we cannot but ſée how the caſe ſtandeth in euery of vs, each man in himſelfe: for he taketh a ſimilitude from a ſower of corne, which going &amp; caſting his ſéed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, it lighteth vpon ſundrie kinds of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: ſome falleth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way ſide, where the path is trampled &amp; beaten ſmooth &amp; hard, by mens féet, &amp; is made like a paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; there it lieth aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vncouered, the Fowles come by and by and picke it vp.</p>
            <p>Some falleth into ſtony ground or roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky, or as S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith vpon a rocke: where ther is a little thin cruſt of earth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top, &amp; ſome moiſture in which the ſéed is a little couered: &amp; becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth which doth couer it is but ſhallowe, it ſpringeth vp quickly &amp; brauncheth, &amp; is freſh &amp; gréene, &amp; being ſo good, ſéemeth to be forward corne, &amp; ſuch as would yéeld to the huſbandman a plentifull harueſt:
<pb facs="tcp:18869:5"/>
but becauſe the roote can not ſpreade it ſelfe déepe inough to ſucke iuice out of the ground, for the nouriſhment of the blade, when the parching heate of the Sunne lighteth vpon it, then it is dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp, and ſcorched, and dyeth, and neuer bringeth foorth fruite. Some other doth fall among thornes: there is deapth of earth for the ſéede to growe, ſo that it ſpringeth vp, and not onely a blade, but alſo a ſtalke, and commeth ſo farre as to haue the eare: but the thornes growe vp with it, ouerſhadowe and choake it, inſomuch that the Corne in the eare, can not haue the benefit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne to make it ripe: therefore the fruite that it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bring forth commeth to naught. Some other ſéeds fall into good ground, and grow vp, and bring foorth ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fruite, one karnell an hundreth, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſixtie, another thirtie. This is the Parable: Now for the meaning of it, we are not to ſéeke farre, neither to goe by coniectures, for Chriſt himſelfe doeth expound and interprete euery part of it a little after in this Chapter: I néed not but to lay open his Expoſition.
<pb facs="tcp:18869:6"/>
The ſéede is the word of God: the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it is the Preacher and publyſher of the ſame: for as the Sower doth fill his hand and ſo caſteth it abroad vppon the ground, not ſetting it ſéede by ſéede, or chooſing a place for euerie ſéede, but where it lighteth: euen ſo the Preacher doth caſt foorth the word among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and looke how the ground is into which it falleth, ſo doth it proſper: for your hearts are the ground vpon which it is caſt: you that are the hearers and among whom the ſéede is ſowen, haue euery one a heart which is one of theſe foure ſorts of grounde, vpon which the ſéede falleth: &amp; becauſe the ſéede hath ben &amp; is ſtill daily ſowen among ye, I think this parcell of Scripture is verie fit and agréeable: euen as a touchſtone for euery one to trie himſelfe withall, whether he haue rightly embraced the Goſpell, and to his ſaluation: for what a ſottiſhneſſe were this, when we haue ſo iuſt &amp; plain a rule, not to meaſure our ſelues with it. But going on, on, nothing conſider whether we be not one of thoſe thrée euill ſorts of ground, which receiue the
<pb facs="tcp:18869:6"/>
ſéede, but bring foorth no fruite, thinking we be well if we profeſſe the Goſpell or heare it, after any ſort. Let vs goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: thoſe which receyue the ſéede by the waye ſide, are they which heare the word and doe not vnderſtand it, then commeth the euill one, or as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, the Diuell, and taketh it awaye from their heart. In theſe firſt kinde of hearers, we haue to obſerue, how that their hearts being hard and ſmooth lyke a path that is trampled and beaten with mens féete y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word hath no entrance, but lieth aboue vncouered: for like as when a man caſteth an handful of corne vpon a very hard &amp; ſmooth path, it is all one as if it were caſt vpon a pauement: ſo alſo through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome &amp; deceitfulnes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harts of theſe vnméet to receiue the heuenly ſéed of the word: &amp; looke how ye ſée Crowes &amp; other foules folow the héeles of the Sower, to picke vp &amp; deuoure ſuch karnells as doe lie vncouered: in like manner doe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels come like gréedie foules into the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, wher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to take it away from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearts of the
<pb facs="tcp:18869:7"/>
people, that it may not grow there. This peraduenture will ſéeme ſtraunge to ſome, that Satan ſhoulde haue anye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce into the Church among Gods people, eſpecially when they be about the beſt and moſt holy exerciſes of hearing the word and of prayer. How ſtraunge ſoeuer it may ſéeme, and how many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer haue bene, or be of that fond &amp; dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh opinion, to thinke that the Diuell hath nothing to doe with them, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not néere them, when they bée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe holye things: we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue Chriſt who telleth vs the contrary: &amp; we are wiſely to conſider, that when we are nighteſt that which ſhould do our ſoules good, then is this enimie readieſt at hande, and doeth moſt buſely beſtirre him. If this were not vttered by our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe, we might wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and for mine owne parte I woulde not ceaſe wondering to ſee manye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers which carry away almoſt nothing which is to any purpoſe: let a man tell a long ſtorie in a worldly matter, they haue wit inough to recite it in order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and to kéepe it in remembraunce
<pb facs="tcp:18869:7"/>
a long time after: but let the Preacher ſpeake neuer ſo plaine, although they ſit and looke him in the face, yet if ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of them ſo ſoone as they be out at the Church dores, ye ſhal eaſely perceiue that (as the common ſaieng is) it went in at the one eare, and out at the other. They will ſay peraduenture, after this manner, It was a good Sermon, I wold we could follow it: he ſaid very well: he is a perfect ready man in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. But aſke, what doctrine did he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle? Then are they at a pauſe, and ſet at a dead lift. They will make this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: we are not able to carry awaye ſo much as other can, neuertheleſſe we hope that we be as good toward God, as they that carry away moſt. They will alſo confeſſe that the word of God is good, and that we ſhould be ruled by it. Let vs therefore déerely beloued, (if we deſire not to be of the number of theſe) marke well the ſubtill ſleights, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of the Diuell, how he handeleth &amp; conueyeth the matter with this kinde of people. There is no doubt of this, but that if he can he will drawe awaye the
<pb facs="tcp:18869:8"/>
minde from comming to the Sermon, one pelting let or other muſt come in the waye: if there be no worldlye buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be done: then a paire of cardes or tables or ſome honeſt recreation, it ſhould be now no good ciuilitie to parte companye when friendes are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: this is the ſureſt waye if it maye be obtained: but what if he faile héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? They come to the place where the ſéede-ſhall be ſowen, ſit downe, &amp; minde to heare: then the next way is to come with them, and to attend at their elboe, ſéeking how to depriue them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word. Now his beſt way is to bring them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſléepe becauſe they were then as good bée abſent: or into a ſlumber, that they maye heare onely a ſound and a confuſed hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, without any perſeuerance of the things vttered: or els when they heare any perfect ſentence, or a few ſentences, they know not why they be vttered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hard not that which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Such as are not ſo drouſie headed, being wakeful, he ſéeketh ſtill to conuey ſome thoughts into their minds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts they may be occupied, and theyr
<pb facs="tcp:18869:8"/>
vnderſtanding drawen away: the minde of a man being light and inconſtant, if he can put in but one motion, it often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times draweth with it ſo manye lynkes as make vp a whole chaine, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time the Preacher goeth on, and he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not what was ſayd, &amp; ſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his minde retourneth, he can haue no ſound knowledge of the things vttered, but a confuſed opinion: into theſe by thoughts, men are oftentimes brought, euen by occaſion of ſome word or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which they heard vttered, &amp; are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſo far, that they cannot of long time recouer their minde to bring it again to the matter. Séeing this great danger, we ought when we come to heare Gods word taught, to make accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we go about a very hard worke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we go to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand to hand, who ſeketh then moſt buſily to ſteale away our hart: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word fruitles in vs, &amp; cauſe vs to ſinne greuouſly againſt God. Ther is no one man which maketh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of hearing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word rightly, which ſetting theſe things together, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we owe vnto it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtedines of our mind,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:9"/>
which ſhould be vpon it, and the care to kéepe it, but will eaſily graunt that it is as hard and painful a trauell to do this, as for the man that worketh in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt bodely labour. Héere is therefore a leſſon for euery man to apply to himſelf when he is going to heare the word, to thinke, I am now going about a great worke, I ſhall be too weake if the Lorde God doe not mightelye aſſiſt me: for I am not to ſit down there at eaſe, but to wraſtle and ſtruggle with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, &amp; with all the corruptions of mine owne fleſh, and hardneſſe of my heart: that my minde maye be kept ſtedfaſt vpon the word, that I maye receiue it with all reuerence &amp; feare, as the worde of the great and glorious God: not to iudge of it at mine owne pleaſure, but to craue wiſedome from the Lord: not to heare it and to let it go, but to kéep it as a moſt precious Iewell locked vp in my heart, that I may guide my ſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. And we ſhall be a great deale the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moued to this diligence, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a companion we carie about with vs, and what a gueſt we lodge
<pb facs="tcp:18869:9"/>
withall, when we he ſuch as heare the word, and doe not kéepe it. For Chriſt telleth vs that it is the diuell which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this: which as a gréedie Fowle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth the ſéede which was ſowen in our heart: if any make none account to haue him poſſeſſing their minde, &amp; harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their harts againſt the word: then let them continue in their ſloth to heare with drouſie minds, to heare &amp; not to vnderſtand: to regard the holy word, but as the word of a man: to make little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to kéepe it. But if he thinke it a moſt miſerable thing to haue ſo filthy a beaſt, and ſo foule a ſpirit to lodge in his breſt: if he thinke it to be a moſt vile ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, to be vanquiſhed &amp; ouercome of ſo horrible an enimy, to be lead captiue &amp; kept thrall vnder ſuch a tyrant: then let him thinke alſo how miſerable a thing it is to be ſuch a kind of ground as doth receiue the ſéede by the way ſide: for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly howſoeuer men ſeeme to defy the diuell, and curſe him as though he ſhould not come nigh them, yet ſéeing it is no mortall man but the Lord Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, who telleth vs héere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18869:10"/>
the diuell is not onely nigh, but in theſe kinde of hearers, euen hardening theyr heartes, &amp; blinding their eies, we ought moſt conſtantly to beléeue it. He that ſhall déeply weigh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of our church at this day, wil ſoone be brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that there be many of this firſt ſort of hearers, they ſhall perceiue it right well by this, that they are not able in any wiſe to iudge or put difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene ſound and ſincere preaching, and vaine pratling: they know not when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Preacher doth miniſter vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome foode, &amp; when there is nothing but chaffe &amp; winde: ye ſhal heare them high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend ſome Sermon, as a matter worthy to be written in letters of gold, when as indéed it deſerueth not ſo much as to be noted with a coale. I ſpeak not of thoſe ſily wretches, which were neuer as yet acquainted with preaching, for it is no great maruell, though they be not able to diſcerne chalke from chéeſe: or being blind for to iudge of coulours, but to ſuch as long time haue ben hearers, &amp; yet neuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſer, becauſe they are not able to iudge when ſound and neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:18869:10"/>
concluſions are drawne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word: but is al one with them, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is made be good or bad, ſtrong or weake: yea further ye ſhall perceiue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euen a little ſhew of a reaſon although neuer ſo doltiſh, being againſt true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, doth more preuaile with them, then a multitude of infallible proofes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be neuer ſo ſure: and that which is ſo groſe &amp; abſurd that a childe may laugh at, ſéemeth to them a verye ſtrong piller to leane vnto. Ther néedeth no more when a man preacheth vnto them, but a glorious ſhew of learning, a ſwéet ringing voice, &amp; matters ſo ſtrange &amp; ſtraungely handeled, that they may be brought into a wonderment of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they know not. And Satan hath many chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines fit for this turne, to ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vain humor of ſuch people, &amp; to ſet forth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues after a pompous ſort: more ſéeking their owne vaine glory, then the glorye of the Goſpell, in the conuerſion of the people. The ſecond kinde of ground are they which receiue the ſéed vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard rock, where ther is ſome entrance, &amp; the word hath a ſhallow root in them, for as
<pb facs="tcp:18869:11"/>
it were the top of their heart is ſoft af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort, and there it is couered a litle, &amp; it groweth vp quickly, and ſpringeth freſh, they ſéeme to be ſtout and excellent profeſſours, they brag of great zeale: a man would take them to be ſincere, &amp; ſo they take themſelues: but when the Sun ariſeth, that is, the firie trial or parching heat of perſecution, they ſtumble &amp; fal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and becauſe the word had no déepe roote in them, it withereth and bringeth forth no fruit: theſe alſo are not profited by the word of grace, but are ſtil caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and damned creatures: in this kinde of ground, or in theſe hearers, if we note well, we ſhall ſée that which is ſtraunge and wonderfull: when Chriſt ſayth and teſtifieth of them, that they receiue the word with ioy: theſe hée not blaſphemers or perſecutors of the word: they be not contemners which regarde not at all to heare it: they come not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſhew or pretence as to a thing which otherwiſe they haue no care nor féeling of, or which they delight not for to heare, but how? They receiue it with ioy, &amp; take ſuch pleaſure therein, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
<pb facs="tcp:18869:11"/>
they can ſay, ſurely this was a very notable péece of worke &amp; wel han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled, I am glad that I heard it, it doth me euen as much good as my meate, I would go a mile to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like again. Is not this then meruailous and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that a man may goe thus far, &amp; yet be a caſtaway, and a forlorne wretch? It is not a thing to be wondered at when the holy ſcriptures giue ſentence againſt thoſe traiterous villaines which ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt God, and tread down his laws: but when God vttereth this ſharp ſentence againſt this zealous kinde of men, if it cauſe vs not to wonder, yet it may make vs to tremble, when we ſee y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a man may procéed thus far in religion &amp; yet be damned. When we vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may be zealous, &amp; redy to heare preaching, vnderſtandeth, carrieth away, letteth it grow in his hart, hath ſome ioy in it, and yet neuer the better, abiding ſtill vnder the curſe. But there be ſome which will obiect againſt me &amp; ſay, this is no good manner of teaching, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of true teaching is to build vp and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith: but this ſéemeth to take away
<pb facs="tcp:18869:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the certeintie of faith from al, ſo that no man can tell whether he ſhall be ſaued: For by what meanes can a man make a better triall &amp; proofe of his faith then this, that he giueth eare to Gods word, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it, carieth it away, &amp; ioyeth in it? If ſuch a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be damned, who may not diſpaire? I auni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>were with S. <hi>Paule. 1. Cor. 10. 12.</hi> He that thinketh he ſtandeth, let him take héed he do not fal. If y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> admonition were neceſſary to the <hi>Corinthes,</hi> it is neceſſary for vs al One of the principall ends &amp; vſes of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is to giue men warning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they doe not deceiue themſelues with euery kind of faith or ioy in the word: but to looke for good &amp; ſound triall in themſelues: which is not the way to bring men to diſpaire, but to bring them to true god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: to cauſe them to ſhake of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; looſeneſſe in the ſeruice of God: to beware leaſt their heartes be hard ſtill within: it cauſeth men to try the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues leaſt they ſhuld be deceiued by a vaine ſhadow of a dead &amp; fruitleſſe faith: for Chriſt ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe beléeue (for ſo it is expreſſed by S. Luke the 8. 13.) &amp; ioy in
<pb facs="tcp:18869:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the word, and yet are damned. Then let vs come to the particular applieng of this point: to ſée howe wée are to deale with our ſelues. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word take héede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye giue it depth of earth inough, looke that your heart be not ſoft and pliable inough a little aboue, and a hard rocke of ſtone within, but ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be digged and ſoftened to the bottome, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the word may take root déepe inough. Alas, what a miſerable thing is it, when Chriſt hath giuen vs warning héere ſo plainly, for a man to be a zealous Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peller, not onelye willing to heare, but hath an earneſt deſire, and trauelfeth to heare, taketh pleaſure &amp; delight when he heareth, yet neuertheles, becauſe he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no héed therto, his heart within is ſo ſtony, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he heareth but to his further increſe of damnation. Many think it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when as they receiue this teſtimonie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men: he is a ſound Proteſtant, he fauoureth &amp; delighteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, theſe indéed be great tokens of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> feare of god, but yet we are not to reſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: our chiefe dealing is betwéene God &amp; our heart: &amp; that in this thing whether
<pb facs="tcp:18869:13"/>
our heart be not hard and rockie. Thoſe are a thouſand times happie, which féele melting hearts &amp; ſoft affections, ſo that Gods word doth pearſe into them, and cauſeth them to tremble at the maieſty &amp; power of the ſame: their tender heart doth ſigh &amp; mourne for their iniquitie. As on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary part, they which make no conſcience of ſinne, but are hardened in their affections, although they ſéeme to be in good caſe, yet are they curſed and miſerable. Let euery man therefore that goeth from the Sermon, carry this with him: I heare by Chriſtes owne words y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a ſtonie ground where the ſéede falleth: where it groweth but not déep inough, it ſpringeth vp but doth not bring forth fruite, this is a wofull caſe, if I ſhould be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of theſe, for then all my labour is loſt, which I beſtow in frequenting Sermons, yea, it were much better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had neuer heard: I féele that I ioy in it, I would not for any thing but I had heard it: but Chriſt ſaith that the reprobate, ſome of them do heare the word with ioy, ſo that if I looke not narrowly to mine owne hart,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:13"/>
I may for all this be damned: therfore I muſt not ſatiſfie my ſelfe with this, but ſee that I couer the worde déepe inough, that my heart be ſoftned in ſuch ſort, that I féele the roote goeth déepe, yea, ſo déepe, that it can neuer bée rooted out: And therefore let him continually crie vnto God and ſay: O Lord make ſofte my harde and ſtonie heart: let it be a melting heart, that thy holy worde may growe in it for euer. I woulde to GOD, this doctrine of our Sauiour Chriſt, might make euerye of vs to tremble and ſhake (as indéede if it were well weighed, it is ſo fearfull, that it might cauſe the haire of our heades to ſtand vp) for then would we not ſo looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſecurely walke in the hardnes of our hearts: there would not be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye backſliders in time of perſecution: there would not be ſo many braue boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and praters of Religion, who are ready to pull in their horns, and to kide their heades, ſo ſoone as there is anye feare of daunger, or lykelyhoode of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: neither would men beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in hand that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e iolly Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:14"/>
when they haue but a little taſted of the word, and are no more but emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie barrels, which giue a great ſounde. Héere then we be ſet a work with great toyle, to haue this ſame harde ſtonye ground made ſoft, and fit to receiue this heauenlye ſéede. And he which is not carefull in this poynt, to take paines, ye ſhall ſée him waxe ſo hard, that euen as a continuall rayne dropping vppon a Rocke of ſtone maketh it neuer the ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo nothing can make his heart to relent. This may teach vs then to ceaſe maruelling, when we ſée ſo many which willingly giue themſelues to be taught, and haue ſtill little remorre of ſinne. The Lord for his mercie ſake make vs wiſe and ſharpe ſighted to iudge of our ſelues: not to be leade on forwarde in a carnall profeſſion, but to giue credite to our heauenlye teacher, who hath héere opened his holy mouth to inſtruct vs ſo plainlye, and before hande to warne vs of the great daunger: that we may ſtir vp our ſelues, and de quickened in our dull ſpirits, with all humble ſubmiſſion, and boowing downe our neckes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb facs="tcp:18869:14"/>
the doctrine of our Lorde, and to open our heartes in ſuch ſorte that hée may digge in them, and thruſt in his ſpade to the bottome. For otherwiſe, it cannot goe well with vs. If this wer practiſed among vs, we ſhoulde not haue ſo many olde ruſtie Proteſtants: which if a man talk with them from morning to night, they are able to continue ſpeach in reciting ſtories and places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and will vtter matter agaynſt the doctrine of the Pope: but let a man vrge them with the doctrine of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and ſtande vpon the neceſſitie of ſincere repentaunce, ſhowing them that they muſt be trulye humbled vnder the burthen of theyr ſinnes, that they muſt mortifie and ſubdue their carnall luſts: this is to hard a cruſt for their old téeth. This matter doth marre all: this doeth robbe them of their glorie: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot willynglye abide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to heare of it. Let vs come now to the third kinde of ground, which receyueth the ſéed among the thorns: héere is depth inough of earth: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the ſecond ſort of hearers ſéemed to go far beyond the firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:15"/>
ſo theſe ſéeme to goe farre beyond them, and to come nigher to eternall life, for héere the word doth grow and hath roote ſo déepe, that it ſpringeth foorth ſo farre, that Chriſt ſaith it groweth vp, and the thornes grow vp with it, the ſtalk doth ſhoote foorth the eare, and lacketh but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. For this may be proued by Saint Luke, who ſaith that they be not (Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſphorountes) that is, ſuch as beare ripe and timely fruite: for theſe profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors doe many good workes, and ſéeme to bring forth the fruites of the Goſpell: and that in ſuch wiſe that men cannot alwayes diſcerne them, but thinke their déedes to be notable: but Chriſt Ieſus doth ſhew that their works before God, (who onely cannot be deceyued) are as Corne which lacketh riping, which bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerſhadowed with buſhes, withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the eare and commeth to naught: this is a daungerous caſe if we looke not to it: That a man may heare the Goſpell preached, carrie it away, be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thereby to doe many good workes: and yet be damned. He is a thouſande folde madde therefore, which doeth not
<pb facs="tcp:18869:15"/>
looke to himſelfe in this point: to trye what ſoundneſſe there is in the fruits of his faith, and how ſincerely he doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Gods word. As before I ſayde, that ſome would obiect and ſay, this wil deſtroy the faith, ſo am I ſure that héere it will be ſaid much more: becauſe this ſéemeth to take away the ſureſt tryal of faith: if a man may not by and by ſaye, I haue good workes, therefore I haue the true and lyuely faith: I aunſwere, that whoſoeuer hath any good worke in him, the ſame hath the true faith, which hath brought foorth that good worke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is impoſſible without faith to do any good thing, or to haue any good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or intent: but withall I ſaye, that it is one thing to ſéeme good before men, and another thing for to be good indéede before God. In outwarde appearaunce, there is little difference betwéene the good déeds of them which feare God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and the vntimely fruite of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngs: but God whoſe eye doth not looke vpon the outward ſhew, but the inward affection, ſéeth which procéedeth of faith, and which doth procéede of vaine glorie,
<pb facs="tcp:18869:16"/>
or ſome other ſiniſter reſpect, &amp; putteth as great difference betwéene them, as he did betwéen the ſacrifices of <hi>Cayn</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel.</hi> We muſt take héed then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fruits of our faith be ripe &amp; timely, otherwiſe they be good but in ſhew. We muſt come then to ſée firſt what theſe thorns are: in S. <hi>Mathew</hi> they are called, the cares of this world &amp; the deceitfulnes of riches: in Saint <hi>Luke:</hi> the cares of riches, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this lyfe. And in very deed, theſe thornes doe grow together. For were it not for the pleaſures of this life, there would be no cares of riches: he which doth ſéeke gréedelye for wealth, it is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he woulde be able to haue wherewithall to fill the luſts of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> fleſh, and to pamper his body delicately: or els to ſet forth himſelfe in pride, &amp; to clyme ambitiouſly to honour. For ſo long as a man doth take pleaſure in any of theſe, ſo long he is couetous &amp; raketh together ſo much, that as the common ſaieng is, he raketh vp the Diuell and all. What muſt we doe then? Our heartes are as a ground that is ranke, &amp; bringeth foorth many wéeds: we are ſet a work as God
<pb facs="tcp:18869:16"/>
ſpeaketh by his Prophet <hi>Ieremy.</hi> chap. 4. 4. Plow vp your falow, &amp; ſow not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thorns: we muſt put all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; care y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our hearts may be rid of ſuch noiſome wéeds as will choke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, &amp; make that it ſhal not bring forth fruit in vs. So long as we ſuffer any of theſe in vs, either to loue daintie &amp; dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate féeding of our fleſh, and to fill our ſelues with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> luſts thereof, or to be gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eies of men, &amp; hautely to lift vp our ſelues in our vainglorious mindes, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maintenance of theſe delights bend our care to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: ſo long ſhall we be vnprofitable ſcholers in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſchool of Chriſt. Alas poore men which wold faine come to God, &amp; yet are glewd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, they offer one hand to Chriſt, &amp; the other to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuel: they can talke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit, &amp; yet are led by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel is in their mouth, &amp; couetouſneſſe lodgeth in their hearts: their workes gliſter &amp; are gréene before men, and are withered before God: they ſéeme to be faithfull &amp; are faithles, to be heires of glory, &amp; yet are the children of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther are great ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of theſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp; ſpecialy in ſuch places, wher ther
<pb facs="tcp:18869:17"/>
is wealth and honours: how many fall away cheked with the world? And yet we are not afraid of our ſelues to take héede that we ſtand faſt. A great mercie of God it is that we haue not onely the doctrine layed before vs, but alſo fearfull examples: ſo that we may buy our wit with other mens coſt. For when we ſée the world with delights and pleaſures, with conetouſneſſe and ambition, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie away thoſe which profeſſe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, is not our owne matter in hande, are not we made of the ſame mettall they are, doth not the world aſſault vs as it doth them? Yes, and we ſhalbe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come alſo, if the Lorde haue not mercie vpon vs. The hardneſſe of this worke, ought not to diſcorage or make vs ſlack, but hearing what Chriſt ſaith, whome we ought to beléeue, the more harde, the more we are to ſtirre vp our ſelues, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we make ſmall reckoning of the ſaluation of our ſoules. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall yéeld and giue ouer the digging vp of theſe thornes, becauſe he perceiueth they grow déepe in his heart, and ſpring as faſt as he can cut them: is not worthy to enter
<pb facs="tcp:18869:17"/>
into life: be which will not continually till and wéede this grounde, may well haue the Goſpell in ſome ſorte for to grow in him, but not to ſaue him. Déer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued we muſt be ſurely perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of this, that as there be many godly men, ſo haue they atteined it with great labour and toile, yea, they are ſtill ſet a worke and cannot come to an end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe thornes cannot be vtterlye ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted out.</p>
            <p>Thoſe are greatly ouerſéene which thinke it to be an eaſie thing to profeſſe Chriſt vnto ſaluation: &amp; make no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account but to bée Goſpellers, at eaſe: if they can vanquiſh in diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to thinke they haue won the field: no, no, they haue a heart which is harde to ouercome: they haue thornes which wil not eaſily be deſtroied: héere lieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and getting of the ſpurs: this man ſhall be crowned becauſe he hath wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly giuen vp himſelfe to the power of Gods grace to purge his heart, and to make roome for the holy worde, that it may grow there alone, and not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed and choaked.
<pb facs="tcp:18869:18"/>
Now let vs marke well that which is ſayde héere, both of the ſtonie and alſo of the thornie ground, how farre they procéede in profeſſing Chriſt, and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his Goſpell: and we ſhall plainely ſée, how greatly thoſe carnal Goſpellers which will not haue faith to be tried by the fruits, are deceiued: Faith, faith, (ſay they) is that which doth iuſtifie, it is true indéede, but not a fruitleſſe faith: whoſoeuer beléeueth ſhal be ſaued: it is euen ſo, but not after euery kinde of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe: for then why ſhould not theſe two ſorts of herers be ſaued, it is meruailous when the Scripture is ſo euident, &amp; our ſauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh ſo plainly, that this groſe &amp; doltiſh errour ſhoulde poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the minds of ſo many. But indéed it is a ſwéet doctrine, when a man may let looſe the raines to all the luſts of the ſleſh, at the leaſt thus farre, not to vere &amp; torment himſelfe in ſubduing them, &amp; yet by faith to be ſaued. When heauen &amp; hell méete together, and God and the diuel be reconciled, then ſhal theſe fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Epicures, and vaine proude men come to their happineſſe. When Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:18869:18"/>
ſhall denie that which he hath héere vttered, then ſhall theſe bée true belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</p>
            <p>Let men therfore take héede that they be not deceiued, nor made ſlacke in look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fruits of their faith &amp; morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of vaine fleſhly luſts, through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophane pratling of ſuch worldly belly Gods: beléeue not them, but beléeue Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who telleth you that it is not inough to heare the word, &amp; to receiue it with ioy, &amp; to let it grow in vs, vnleſſe it bring forth reaſonable and timelye fruit in vs.</p>
            <p>Againe, let vs marke how ſtrong and inuincible an Argument may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of this text againſt all contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and deſpiſers of the word, ſuch as care not for hearing: theſe thrée ſorts of hearers, are before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; néerer to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie then they, and yet come ſhort: therefore it muſt néeds follow, that ſuch ignorant Atheiſts, as neither know, nor deſire to knowe any thing aboue this world, are very far from God, although they would ſéeme with their mouth &amp; lips to draw néere vnto him. For if this
<pb facs="tcp:18869:19"/>
matter were well obſerued, men would not regard nor haue thoſe men in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to be good &amp; honeſt, who are very dogs or ſwine, not regarding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious pearle of the Goſpel, but redy to bark &amp; bite at thoſe which bring it. Let a man inquire thus, not of a few, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of men, how ſaie yée to ſuch a man, what thinke ye of him? he is (ſaye they) a verye good man, a good natured man, a gentle perſon truſtie to his frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſure of his word, &amp; doth kéepe as good an houſe as anye man of his calling in all this ſhire. But how is he affected vnto Gods word: is he zealous in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Nay ſurely, I did neuer heare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did deale y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> way, he is a very quiet man, no medler at al. O notable honeſt man, as deuout in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laws of God as the horſe which he rideth vpon, as careful to haue gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie aduaunced, as the ſwine in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie, a great deale behinde theſe vnprofitable hearers, which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> waies: &amp; yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth being very bruit beaſts before God (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate they be in, yet vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord call them to bée zealous of his glorye) they muſt be reputed for the beſt men.
<pb facs="tcp:18869:19"/>
Our fieldes are full of ſuch Cattell as theſe, and if the Lord do not put too his helping hand; our caſe is very miſerable. If any of thoſe which were ſo zealous to heare, that they woulde to their hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deraunce in worldly matters leaue off their buſineſſe, and follow preaching, as theſe which flocked to heare Chriſt, wer yet neuertheleſſe relected, becauſe they did not ſo ſincerely as they ſhould: what ſhal we ſay of thoſe which wil not ſtep out at their dores, euen when they haue nothing to do, vnles it be to ſit at cards or tables. If ſuch a man maye be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as is mooued with ſome delight, when he heareth the worde preached: What ſhall we iudge of thoſe woodden blockes and ſottiſh men, who féele no more ioye in it then a poſt, when it is vttered vnto them? If ther be ſome go to deſtruction, which conforme themſelues and haue a ſhew of fruite by the worde: wher ſhal thoſe wretches appeare, whom the holy word of God cannot moue one whit, to reforme their diſordered &amp; beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiours. I néede not ſtande to mueigh out of this place againſt thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:18869:20"/>
helhounds, which dare ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouths to reproch and ſlaunder the ſetting forth of the Goſpell. The Lord diminiſh the number of them.</p>
            <p>The laſt kind of ground, are the good hearers, which do not onely receiue the ſéede, but alſo bring forth the fruits ther of. Although not euery one a lyke or in the ſame meaſure, for ſome bring forth an hundreth folde, ſome ſixtie fold, ſome thirtie folde, according to the meaſure of Gods graces in them.</p>
            <p>Although héere be great ods in brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth the fruits, yet they be all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and accompted for good grounde, true Chriſtians, and ſincere profeſſors of godlineſſe: now as we be taught héere that it is required of all to be doers, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, and not hearers only cha. 1. ver. 22. ſo are we alſo taught, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe or raſhly to condemne thoſe, which do not bring forth ſo great a meaſure of fruit as others do: True it is, as Chriſt ſaith, héerein is my father glorified, that ye bring forth much fruite. <hi>Iohn. 15. 8.</hi> But it is alſo as true which he ſaith in the ſecond verſe of the ſame chapter, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb facs="tcp:18869:20"/>
braunch that bringeth forth fruite, he purgeth, that it may bring forth more fruite. Then to bring forth moſt, is moſt of all to be deſired, that God maye haue the greateſt glory: to bring forth the leaſt is not to be contemned, becauſe the Lord in time doth purge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; make them more fruitfull. I néed not to ſtand héere for to handle manye things, or to make large expoſition, the matter is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding plaine, ther is no more but this, that all our care in hearing &amp; profeſſing the Goſpell, be to receiue it into good ground, and to bring forth the fruites thereof. What ſhould I ſtand to rip vp the ſhamefull abuſe in the contrary, to vtter how manie euill fruits ther be in many which are Goſpellers. This ſhuld be but as it were to light a candle in the cléere Sun ſhine, for all men do ſée them. I do not ſpeake this, as though it ſhould not be good to crie out againſt them: but becauſe the former things which I haue now vttered, doe fully diſcloſe them. And therefore I will héere ende, deſiring the Lord to write theſe things in our harts, which we haue heard with our outward
<pb facs="tcp:18869:21"/>
eares, and to make vs good ground, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the heauenly ſéede, &amp; to bring forth fruites of the ſame, that glorifieng him in this world, we may be glorified of him in the world to come, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
